So the first step we're going to learn today is the three-step process of establishing an intent system
Step one, learn intent analysis
before you perform intent recognition
You need to have an intent system
In other words, before you let the model recognize,
you manually determine how many intents there are in this scenario
then how these intents are categorized
what the relationships between them are
you already have a clear understanding
Only after manual familiarization can the model then perform the task
This is the most fundamental and unchanging principle in developing AI products.
If the manual understanding of the techniques involved is not familiar
then it's basically impossible to have the model handle this task
So what we're doing here is first establishing an intent system
so that we can manually clarify all the intents in this domain
and then hand it over to the machine model to learn
Only after learning can there be evaluation
can we optimize product issues
OK, everyone needs to understand this relationship
First and foremost, as I just mentioned
We just discussed
Master intent analysis
First, we need to ask a question
What is user intent
Let's look at a few examples first
The first scenario: food delivery customer service
The user asks about the beef soup they ordered
The beef soup spilled, what the hell am I supposed to eat now?
The second one is about the hotel scenario, where the user asks if pets are allowed in this hotel.
The third one, e-commerce customer service scenario
The user asks, 'It's been days already'
Why hasn't it shipped yet
What are the user intents corresponding to these inquiries?
You can pause and think about it
What are the user intents to be identified for these inquiries?
What is more important is the principle
These three are actually completely different scenarios
also have different ways of asking
but they share a unified principle
It's actually guiding them from behind to conduct this kind of analysis
This kind of training is truly crucial
AI products must learn to infer intentions from users' various behavioral data.
Let's look at the first example: the ordered beef soup was completely spilled.
There may be several labeled answers
First, let's talk about the anger intent
The user is clearly very angry
Emotion recognition is crucial
so it's an anger intent
The second one is the small talk intent
because the user has not provided an actionable goal
He's just complaining.
The third one is
This is clearly a complaint about the delivery rider.
It was most likely caused by the delivery rider.
The fourth one
Apply for meal compensation, the user's beef soup was spilled
what I ordered was the soup
That money was wasted
He definitely wants to get compensated for the loss.
Now, let's take a look at how to identify the main intent in this case.
As we mentioned before
that is to say, if you've seen other tutorials on intent recognition
you might notice, wait a minute
user inquiries aren't all about
Hello, I would like to apply for meal compensation
and hello
I want to book a flight from Beijing to Hangzhou
Then I'll first position, fine-tune the core keywords within the scenario
Then what should I do next? Okay
OK, 99%
But you realize hey
Damn, how come all four of these look so similar?
So this is actually the real situation
because that's exactly how we talk to customer service
very casual
very colloquial
We've always said it's actually a principle guiding our thinking.
The two principles of intent analysis, the first principle
Intent is the purpose
We analyze intent not expressions
is to analyze the user's purpose
for example
someone asks you out to dinner
You want to refuse, so you say, maybe another time
but when you say 'another time'
Do you actually mean to reschedule?
If at this moment, someone responds with
So when exactly do you want to reschedule it to?
You probably wouldn't find this person very considerate
You would think, how could this person be so inconsiderate
Because you said 'some other day'
Actually, your intention is to refuse.
So intention is actually the purpose
What is the second one?
Deduce the intention based on fulfillment actions
In other words, you need to determine what follow-up action to take based on the purpose.
The fundamental goal of our intent recognition is to address users' intentions and needs.
Each type of intent should correspond to a set of actionable responses.
So what exactly is intent analysis?
Intent analysis equals purpose plus
follow-up actions, you might feel a bit confused when I put it this way
Now let's analyze this case briefly
you might understand
First, let's look at the anger intent
What is the corresponding business action for the anger intention?
Right, his goal is definitely to express anger
So what is the corresponding action?
comforting script, but if you think about it
But is it okay for the user experience if I only respond with comforting words?
Right, it's definitely not feasible
So this is first the anger intent
Next, let's examine the idle chat intent
If you identify it as a chit-chat intent
then we let the model chat with the user
What is the follow-up action?
tell a bunch of lies to him
or you simply ignore the user
Then the user gets even angrier
My beef soup has already spilled
I can't even eat my meal
and then you keep babbling on about nonsense
Then this definitely won't work either, right?
The three complaint intents corresponding to the process of reporting the delivery rider
However, first of all, this may not necessarily be caused by the delivery rider.
Even if a complaint is filed, the user's own loss is not compensated.
he would still not be satisfied
Fourth, if the process of applying for meal compensation is followed
If the meal compensation application process was followed
If the situation is true
the user can receive compensation
Secondly, proceed to the meal damage assessment
There will definitely be compensation
and this kind of reassurance would be more specific
If there is a food damage result, it is possible to investigate whether the delivery rider was negligent.
In fact, through this set of processes
It can perfectly address the user's intent.
So, analyzing intent means figuring out the user's goal
then figure out the user's action
Always remember
Analyzing intent is not about analyzing the user's words
but rather what is the primary purpose of this intent
what is his primary purpose
Secondly, what kind of action would be more appropriate to take in response
Let me explain this example again
If you define it as an anger intention
Is the user satisfied?
Dissatisfied You define it as a small talk intent
you define it as a small talk intent
Then you conclude it with small talk, is the user satisfied?
not satisfied either
You define it as a complaint intent, label it as a complaint intent
Then using the complaint process to handle it, is the user satisfied?
The user is dissatisfied
However, the damage assessment process is very likely to satisfy the user.
So what is his intention
his intention is to claim compensation for the damaged food
The most fundamental goal of intent is to have tangible elements, actions, landing pages, and functionalities
and then use appropriate responses to address the user's request
I might subsequently release 100 cases
then everyone labels it
then conduct a small simple exercise
For example, is this hotel pet-friendly?
It is definitely a Q&A objective
But what kind of action should be taken to handle it?
If you set it as a simple question
then you check the hotel policy
Is this really good
If this hotel is truly pet-friendly, OK
The user's needs are met
What if it's not?
Do you think the user's needs have been met?
Or perhaps, do you have a better way
This needs to be considered
The second point is that it's been several days
It's been days and it still hasn't shipped
This is definitely a process for urging delivery.
What kind of action do you think would be more appropriate to handle the order催促 process?
This is something we can all analyze further